<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Wesley Lima]]></title><description><![CDATA[A starter blog demonstrating what Gatsby can do.]]></description><link>https://www.wesleylima.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 22:26:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[What Is Gun Database?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Why Did I Write This I’ve been working on a version of this post for 3 months, but now that Gun is getting more mainstream attention, I feel…]]></description><link>https://www.wesleylima.com/what-is-gun-database/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.wesleylima.com/what-is-gun-database/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Why Did I Write This&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working on a version of this post for 3 months, but now that Gun is getting more &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/jack/status/1352442460127936512&quot;&gt;mainstream attention&lt;/a&gt;, I feel like a third party perspective on Gun and its problems is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/00220/gun_will_fire.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 73.64864864864865%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMFAQT/xAAWAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAWbLYVQOIy//xAAaEAACAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIRIRAS/9oACAEBAAEFArvmEZNHsWn/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAaEAACAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMQECEDKh/9oACAEBAAY/AsuR2NuH/8QAGxAAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERIRBRcdH/2gAIAQEAAT8hXYrWDyKx38x4zTo//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDDL//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAR/9oACAEDAQE/EKf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPxCI/8QAHhABAAICAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFRkUGBodH/2gAIAQEAAT8QLFsXyx3Dw5Znuj3ANQGKS/sC19/4g6crRanU/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Gun Will Fire With Magazine Removed&quot;
        title=&quot;Gun Will Fire With Magazine Removed&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/1c72d/gun_will_fire.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/a80bd/gun_will_fire.jpg 148w,
/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/1c91a/gun_will_fire.jpg 295w,
/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/1c72d/gun_will_fire.jpg 590w,
/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/a8a14/gun_will_fire.jpg 885w,
/static/e57ef328d20590c50dbcad481f1b2451/00220/gun_will_fire.jpg 1059w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Good&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been lurking the gun community (and it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a community) since September 2018. They are very active and are very “newbie friendly”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cool Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conflict-free_replicated_data_type&quot;&gt;CRDTs&lt;/a&gt; which I beleive will be standard is every distributed database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graph databases are cool. A graph is the superset of all data structures. The idea of a Universe of nodes (Graph UNIVERSE Node) that interlink all data is cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Gun fails in the execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Bad&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Misleading Claims and Bad Expectation Management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun makes some outrageous performan comparisons against “real” databases. But as you’ll come to see, comparring gun with “real” databases is laughable. Passing around unecrypted, unsigned, unindexed data with no ACL is actually very computationally easy. Their “conflict resolution algorithm” that syncs data is a lexical comparison. Gun is missing &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;/em&gt; of featuers that “real” databases provide. Without these feature, their performance “metrics” don’t mean anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ease of Use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun people often explain the project like “a open source Firebase!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. It absolutely is not like firebase. The provided API is very obtuse and poorly documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun also has no real ACL layer. Their official soultion is to encrypt object using their “SEA” security library. Except that by doing that, you either have to use their very clunky user system, or roll your own access control in your application.
Out of the box—no matter what they claim— gundoesn’t support selectively sharing user data. With gun either something is public to all, or accessible only to the user that created it. &lt;em&gt;This is not stated in the documentation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can write your own key sharing mechanism using their security library library. But that’s &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; writing and ACL library. It’s not Gun providing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, now that you’re signing/verifying and encrypting/decrypting every node of data, the &lt;em&gt;ultra fast&lt;/em&gt; advertised performance starts making your data load like it’s coming off a 2002 DSL connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newcomers often ask: “Can gun do &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;?” And their answer is without exception always “Yes”. Gun people do leave out the part where it’s not actually Gun that’s doing “x”. It’s you that are going to have to write that feature on top of Gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Access Control&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The universality of the “root graph” is very poorly explained in the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their documentation is full of examples like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Gun([&amp;#39;http://server1.com/gun&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;http://server2.com/gun&amp;#39;])
gun.get(&amp;#39;something&amp;#39;).get(&amp;#39;not&amp;#39;).get(&amp;#39;exist&amp;#39;).get(&amp;#39;yet&amp;#39;).put(&amp;quot;Hello World!&amp;quot;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that ANYBODY can connect to server1.com OR server2.com and modify the contents of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;something.not.exists.yet&lt;/code&gt;
arbitrarily is nowhere prominent in the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do they leave out such critical information for developers? Or use maybe use a realistic, access-controlled or encrypted/signed example? My guess is that it’s because it detracts from the “simple” brand they’re trying to hard to cultivate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you implement “server-side” filtering (yes this serverless peer-to-peer protocol has servers…) through a non-core package, anybody can write anything to any “non special” node on graph. Documentation leaves this detail out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, under the ideal “universal graph”, a non-SEA node can’t exist. But not only does documentation not explain this, all their examples are &lt;em&gt;fundamentally incompatible&lt;/em&gt; with how Gun would be used in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no “official” way to use Gun in the real world. Just some low level, buggy APIs for signing and encrypting. It’s buggy now, but gun knows about and they’re working on it! They’ve been working on this basic funcitonality for over 3 years. Yet they continue to imply Gun as fully featured and production-ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Baffling Tradeoff Choices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;User&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun claims they have dAPP Username and Passwords!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But usernames are not unique. So they they’re of limited usefulness to a developer (or even a user). But yet again it’s marketed without this caveat is completely glossed over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation does a very poor job at explaining (or very good job at obscuring) the surface area of attack that their login system exposes. Your private key are encrypted by your password and then sent through the network. Easy passwords can be cracked trivially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their mitigation for brute force attacks is “proof of work”. What is not mentioned in the documentation is that the “proof of work” is only eforced when a server gets a request for a password. If a malicious server with your encrypted privated key wanted to, they are free to brute force the encrypted private key without providing a POW. &lt;em&gt;THIS IS NOT POINTED OUT DOCUMENTATION&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Obsession With Fringe Features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devloper is obsessed with micro-optimisation at the expense of everything else. In 2020, development essentially halted as the main developer (see #busfactor) worked on a more efficient “CPU Scheduler” to make it so that abnormally large JSON documents could be processed in a timely manner in a free Heroku instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that this was prioritized over a massive slate of breaking bugs and missing features is mind boggling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, most of the 2020 “releases” were unstable. Which is of course extremely confusing for any developer when the “latest release” is actuallybuggy(er) than the a year-older release. Note that this instability wasn’t noted anywhere in the documentation. You had to code along with Gun, find a bug, then go on their Discord and ask a question where (at least quickily) someone would tell you to roll back to last-year’s releaase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developer is irrationally hostile toward any modern Javascript dev tools like ES6 and Promises. This comes out of some vague fixation on extreme “compatibiltiy” and “runs in any browser”. There is no tollerance toward Babel, Polyfills and really any build tools (that aren’t invented at Gun).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did mention the community in “The Good” section. Yes they’re very friendly to newcommers, but the offical Gun people will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; discourage you from using Gun in your project—even if Gun is not a fit for most people at its current state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most community knowledge is siloed in their Discord. Although this is not a unique problem to Gun, it’s especially bad here because the official documentation is seldom updated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the community superficially friendly the founder himself is very unreceptive to criticsm. I’m not the first person to raise some of these concerns. An active member of the community though it be important to add a “disclaimers” as to the suitability of the project. The pull request he made to the documentation with these “caveats” went unmerged for months. When he asked for it to be reviewed or even discussed—he was berated for “feeling entited” to the founder’s time and then subsequently banished from the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is very normal type of disclaimer for software at this stage and is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; informative to developers. Contrast Gun’s exhuberant marketability implications with Orbit’s disclaimer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;NOTE! OrbitDB is alpha-stage software. It means OrbitDB hasn&amp;#39;t been security audited and programming APIs and data formats can still change. We encourage you to reach out to the maintainers if you plan to use OrbitDB in mission critical systems.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From [https://github.com/orbitdb/orbit-db]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project sustainability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is… It’s mathemagical spaghetti. It’s full of micro-optimizations that mostly serve to make the source code illegible. Gun’s author explains this away as coding style or preference. He’s approaching things like a Mathmatician! But even Mathematicians try to use common symbols for clarity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not in Gun though. We have only do obtusely named names here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;	function node(env, at){ var tmp;
		if(tmp = seen(env, at)){ return tmp }
		at.env = env;
		at.soul = soul;
		if(Node.ify(at.obj, map, at)){
			at.link = at.link || Val.link.ify(Node.soul(at.node));
			if(at.obj !== env.shell){
				env.graph[Val.link.is(at.link)] = at.node;
			}
		}
		return at;
	}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;	function valid(v,k,n, at,env){ var tmp;
		if(Val.is(v)){ return true }
		if(obj_is(v)){ return 1 }
		if(tmp = env.invalid){
			v = tmp.call(env.as || {}, v,k,n);
			return valid(v,k,n, at,env);
		}
		env.err = &amp;quot;Invalid value at &amp;#39;&amp;quot; + at.path.concat(k).join(&amp;#39;.&amp;#39;) + &amp;quot;&amp;#39;!&amp;quot;;
		if(Type.list.is(v)){ env.err += &amp;quot; Use `.set(item)` instead of an Array.&amp;quot; }
	}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actual, non-minified source code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only part that of Gun is somewhat comprehensible is the SEA security library. This is probably due to the fact that it was in large part &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; written by the main Gun author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bus Factor=1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of code: while the Gun community is pretty vibrant, there aren’t many contributors to the actual Gun code itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[insert contrib graphs here]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast this with a project like OrbitDb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Orbit db graph]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;amark does the most contribution… and even more scary, he’s probably one of the few people in the planet that actually understands the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Disease&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun suffers from a (hopefully not terminal) case of NIH syndrome. Every problem in the world &lt;em&gt;must be solved by gun&lt;/em&gt; (See freeism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Standards? We Don’t Need No Stinkin’ Standards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standards for cryptographic signed and encrypted JSON objects already exist. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7516&quot;&gt;JOSE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to have been zero effort made to read, understand or extend these existing standards. I’m sure the argument (as always) is “EFFICIENCY”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An actual piece of the code security code with a very helpful comment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;      if(&amp;#39;~@&amp;#39;+key === link_is(val)){ return eve.to.next(msg) } // in fact, it must be EXACTLY equal to itself&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who needs standards when you have &lt;em&gt;performance&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Ecosystem&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realtime P2P database problem that Gun is currently trying to solve is &lt;em&gt;very hard&lt;/em&gt;. No one has really solved it sucessfully yet.
But for &lt;em&gt;some reason&lt;/em&gt;, that’s not enough. They’re creating an an entire “new internet” ecosystem. One Nation Under Gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[ecosystem picture]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Network and Routing “layers” in this ecosystem are &lt;em&gt;insanely difficult&lt;/em&gt; problems on their own. Gun is 0.001% of the way on those fronts. Seeing how little they progressed in the database portion of the ecosystem in the 3 years I have watched them, I don’t see how anyone would have the confidence that this is a realistic objective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P2P Networking and Routing is already being solved by different projects. Some of them &lt;em&gt;in production&lt;/em&gt;! I don’t understand the obsession with Inventing Here when you could collaborate with existing projects that are already solving the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://althea.net/&quot;&gt;Althea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lokinet.org/&quot;&gt;Loki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/&quot;&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.catio.network/&quot;&gt;CatIO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do I not think they can implement their ecosystem, I’m arguing they should not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overreliance of “The Community”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See “Free Software Isn’t Free”.
No successful, sustainable FOSS project runs off vounteerism only. I believe there are only two full time developers working for Gun. And of those two, one is the founder who splits his development time with CEO duties, community management, sales and evangelism. This is obviously not sustainable. &lt;em&gt;Especially&lt;/em&gt; with a developer unfriendy codebase as Gun’s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even basic conventions on how to implement private groups hasn’t been established. They’re still “waiting on the community” to provide a solutionl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the most basic examples are documented. The actual complexity of writing a P2P application with this library is intentionally obfuscated. Simple questions are only answered in “explainer videos” that don’t actually answer the question or refer to aspirational functionality instead of showing real code and use of the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the horribly unprofessional unfinished documentation. This has been this way for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/c0b59/wip.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 45.94594594594595%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAJABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQACBf/EABQBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAD/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAeKaAmP/xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEBAAEFAl//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEBAAY/Al//xAAXEAADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREQ/9oACAEBAAE/IWiEHv8A/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDTz//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABsQAAIBBQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARARAxQVFx/9oACAEBAAE/EIHgTRwXV//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Work In Progress!&quot;
        title=&quot;Work In Progress!&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/1c72d/wip.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/a80bd/wip.jpg 148w,
/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/1c91a/wip.jpg 295w,
/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/1c72d/wip.jpg 590w,
/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/a8a14/wip.jpg 885w,
/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/fbd2c/wip.jpg 1180w,
/static/271bf919aa995df294d7eb6028cb7f1e/c0b59/wip.jpg 1438w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Should you use gun?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be in the cutting edge, be ready to bleed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are better supported P2P ecosystems and platforms that will tell you the truth about current capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is IPFS and Orbit Any Better?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a tool for creating real apps today? Not really. Neither is “production ready”. But one of them lies to you and tells you it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Apendix: Freeism and the Cult of Mark&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to coding P2P database, Gun’s founder also uses the Gun Discord to evangelize a new political phylosophy of his invention: &lt;em&gt;Freeism&lt;/em&gt;.
This might be tangent enough for an entier blog post. Stay tuned.
Spoiler alert: Freeism also is based on Gun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10683467&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10683467&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13249552&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13249552&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitter.im/amark/gun?at=5e13d202e52f6353789762d4&quot;&gt;https://gitter.im/amark/gun?at=5e13d202e52f6353789762d4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amark/gun/pull/854&quot;&gt;https://github.com/amark/gun/pull/854&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/skiqh/gun-cli/tree/b52895b89d1e21004c009682c3766e7a9d1cda5f&quot;&gt;https://github.com/skiqh/gun-cli/tree/b52895b89d1e21004c009682c3766e7a9d1cda5f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Digital Goods]]></title><description><![CDATA[Blockchain is often critized as a solution in search of a problem So here’s an idea for a “blockchain” application that would be useful: The…]]></description><link>https://www.wesleylima.com/digital-goods/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.wesleylima.com/digital-goods/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Blockchain is often critized as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thecorrespondent.com/655/blockchain-the-amazing-solution-for-almost-nothing/84495599980-95473476&quot;&gt;solution in search of a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s an idea for a “blockchain” application that would be useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Hypothetical P2P MMO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose there’s a decentralized MMO game/world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in that world, in-game objects—character appearances, etc—are created by “peers”. Items are not subject to distribution or validation from a central authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could these “peer-created” objects be monetized by their creators?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A creator could “mint” a limited number of copies of his or her digital object. Then sell the digital item to players as a digital “token”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This serves as a form of DRM. But is inherentiy flawd—it tries to restrict access from its intended recipient. It’s especially daunting to consider how it’d be enforced in a P2P system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual data that compose a 3D are not “encrypted”. Only the fact that a user authentically has the right to use said item is enforced by the blockchain. The associating between the data of the asset and the token expressing its ownership is done through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_signing&quot;&gt;code signing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what incentives do players have to this digital ownership? Can’t they just “hack” their game clients to not verify ownership of digital assets?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “hacked” client of the person doing the counterfeiting would be unobstructed by the “DRM”.
But it’s a different story for other players in the online world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since expression or exhibition of some kind of status is the main motivator for these digital items, players would be incentivized to use game clients that check the authenticity of other player’s in-game items. Nobody likes a faker.
For example, if you encountered a player wearing boots that did pass an ownership check, you’d see a “mark of shame” missing texture instead of the desired appearance of the boots.
Note that whatever mark of “forgery” can’t fundamentally “break” the game. This is to ensure there is no incentive to use a game client that tolerates forgeries. The pressures and incentives should be purely social.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strategy is especially effective for “cosmetic” objects — things that don’t grant the player any extra utility or ability. A player would wield such items purely for expressive reasons (skill, wealth, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but they would not have any social benefit from showing off their counterfeit goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we prevent “quick lending” of digital goods? Slow blockchain transaction times in this application serve as a feature rather than a flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why a blockchain though?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couldn’t each creator simply keep a ledger of who bought the digital good? Then each client would check the author’s ledger for authenticity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the intent is for a digital good to not be re-sold (like sadly most DRM’d digital goods are treated today) then this would be a sufficient solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you want to consumers to have the ability to re-sell what they bought and own, then a blockchain starts making sense. You don’t have to rely on the original creator to keep tabs of your business transactions. The supply of the digital good is known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also
Rarity
True Digital good&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collectability factor beyond the in-game appearance.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, an author creates a t-shirt and issues 10 ownership tokens. It turns out the shirts are really popular so she issues 100 more. Then 1000, then 100000.
If you were an owner of the first series of 10 tokens, that might have so collectible value
(I liked them while they were still underground)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Own Your Reality]]></title><description><![CDATA[What is AR AR is the penultimate computing interface. It’s an advancement so profound it will only be superceded by a direct mind machine…]]></description><link>https://www.wesleylima.com/own-your-reality/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.wesleylima.com/own-your-reality/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;What is AR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AR is the penultimate computing interface. It’s an advancement so profound it will only be superceded by a direct mind machine interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it won’t be the last medium—direct mind-machine interfaces are the apex—the leap from smartphones to AR will be the most disruptive and revolutionary ever. It fully replace every medium before it. And it will deeply, literally and irreversibly change the nature of reality itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every medium since we first created media has been exploited to influence behavior and warp perception in ways that benefit the medium”owner” with no regard —and often to the detriment — of the target. This is really just a cute way of saying advertisement and propaganda (the same word in Portuguese). I will call it all propaganda.
As the medium becomes more sophisticated so does the power of propaganda to shape behavior. We know it works because people spend money on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devices become extensions of our selves. This reaches an apex with AR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smartphones already alter human behavior. AR can alter human behavior more powerfully than smartphones by at least a factor of 10
Literally shaping your paradigm at a whim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software on AR computers must BELONG to the user or else we will become slaves to the true owners&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Current State&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Palm Pilot - 1997
iPhone - 2007&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>